Guide to the McKim Mead & White Architectural Records Collection circa 1875-1950 PR 42
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
McKim, Mead & White Architectural Record Collection
circa 1875-1950
PR 42
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
286.0 Linear feet (677 boxes, 13 drawers), plus 15 shelves of bound volumes and 3,046 rolls of architectural drawings
The McKim, Mead & White Architectural Collections consists of architectural drawings, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, financial records, and specifications documenting individual projects of the firm as well as its overall operations.
Scope and Contents note
The McKim, Mead & White Architectural Record Collection spans the period from ca. 1875 to 1950 and includes the major portion of the firm's records. The collection consists of more than 61,000 architectural drawings, including ink on linen, blueprints, and other media; 1,500 photographs, including prints and glass and film negatives; 700 boxes of correspondence and specifications; 54 ledgers, including 17 bill books (1878-1947), 10 cash books (1894-1944), 8 contract books (1903-1930), and 9 journals (1882-1942); 30 photo albums and scrapbooks; and more than 300 original line drawings made to illustrate A Monograph of the Works of McKim, Mead & White, 1879-1915 (all numbers are approximate). The material contains extensive documentation of the firm's operations and of individual buildings, although most information about the firm's early years can be found in the photograph albums, clippings scrapbooks, and financial ledgers.
Included in the collection are Shingle Style, Colonial Revival, and other country houses in Newport, Rhode Island; urban residences such as the Villard Houses, New York; public commissions including Boston Public Library, Rhode Island State Capitol, and Prospect Park entrances, Brooklyn, New York; and universities, museums and libraries including the restoration of the University of Virginia rotunda, Columbia University and Pierpont Morgan Library, New York.
The collection is organized by the following formats: architectural drawings, correspondence, specifications, photographs, scrapbooks and photograph albums, newspaper and journal clippings, financial records, and publications.
More detailed finding aids for portions of the collection are available on-site. Researchers wishing to access the collection must schedule an appointment in advance. Requests for appointments and other questions should be submitted to the librarian for the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Grateful Acknowledgment
The drawings in the McKim, Mead & White collection were re-housed and inventoried with the help of a 2009 grant from the federal Save America's Treasures program.
Provenance
Gift of the firm, 1950 and 1968.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment. Appointments must be scheduled in advance by contacting the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical/Historical note
Charles McKim (1847–1909), William Rutherford Mead (1846–1928), and Stanford White (1853–1906) established their partnership in New York City in 1879 and soon became the premier architectural firm in the United States. Between 1879 and 1912, the firm received nearly 1000 commissions, designing a wide array of residential, institutional, commercial, and public buildings in New York and other cities. Influenced by their extensive travels (and training) in Europe, the firm designed primarily in the Beaux Arts style, becoming the leading proponents of a return to classicism as an expression of American architectural character. The firm's work at the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago in 1893, featuring the "White City," also helped to launch the "City Beautiful" movement.
Among the firm's many notable buildings are Pennsylvania Station (1910, razed 1963), the Morgan Library and Museum (1903, expanded 1928), the Brooklyn Museum (1895), and the Municipal Building (1909-1915).
While associated primarily with the Gilded Age, the firm continued for more than three decades after the death of the last founding partner (Mead) in 1928, and trained many significant 20th century architects, including John Carrere and Thomas Hastings.
Arrangement note
The collection is currently organized by format into the following eight series:
Series I: Architectural drawings
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Specifications
Series IV: Photographs
Series V: Scrapbooks and photograph albums
Series VI: Newspaper and journal clippings
Series VII: Financial records books
Series VIII: Publications
Related Collections at the New-York Historical Society
The personal papers of Stanford White are held by the Library’s Department of Manuscripts.
Related Materials at Other Institutions
Additional McKim, Mead and White drawings and photographs are held by Columbia University's Avery Architectural and Fine Arts Library.
Charles Follen McKim's papers are held by the Library of Congress' manuscript division.
- Series I: Architectural Drawings
  - Subseries I.1: Rolled drawings
    Scope and Contents note
    Included in this series are approximately 61,150 rolled drawings for over 1000 commissioned projects. Approximately 65 percent of these are tracings (mostly ink on linen), and 35 percent are print duplicates (mostly blueprints on paper). They consist of plans, elevations, sections, exterior and interior details, full size details, sketches, and shop drawings. Projects include educational institutions, banks, country estates, residences, clubs and casinos, hotels, memorials, government buildings, public buildings, commercial buildings, libraries, museums, churches, and hospitals in New York and elsewhere.
    The drawings were re-housed between 2009-2012 pursuant to a generous Save America's Treasures grant from the National Park Service, in partnership with the National Endowment for the Arts, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the Institute of Library and Museum Services, and the President's Committee on the Arts and Humanities.
    This subseries includes drawings of many of the firm's most important projects in New York City and elsewhere. An item-level inventory of the rolled drawings is available on-site.
  - Subseries I.2: Flat drawings
    This subseries consists primarily of presentation drawings, but also includes other flattened architectural drawings and a few oversized photographs.
    - Madison Square Garden, plan of eighth floor above roof garden,1894 (Box Flat files, Folder FF1)
    - Madison Square Garden, tower (vellum) (Box Flat files, Folder FF1)
    - Madison Square Garden, elevation of lower part of tower (Box Flat files, Folder FF1)
    - New York University Library, section through reading room (Box Flat files, Folder FF2)
    - House for Mrs. Patterson, Elevation on Burton Place (Box Flat files, Folder FF2)
    - Bank of Montreal interior photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF3)
    - New York Life Insurance Company photo (poor condition) (Box Flat files, Folder FF3)
    - Oakland City Hall competition presentation drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF4)
    - Boston Public Library (Box Flat files, Folder FF5)
    - Washington Arch, Washington Square Park, New York City (Box Flat files, Folder FF5)
    - Washington Arch, Washington Square Park, New York City, front elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF6)
    - Columbia University, drawings on trace (RESTRICTED: needs conservation) (Box Flat files, Folder FF7)
    - Madison Square Presbyterian Church, mounted drawing, front elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF8)
    - Madison Square Presbyterian Church drawing (Box Flat files, Folder FF8)
    - Hotel Nacional, Havana, Cuba, c. 1930, charcoal on board (Box Flat files, Folder FF9)
    - Metropolitan Museum mounted drawing by James Kellum Smitz (Box Flat files, Folder FF10)
    - Mounted color drawing of unidentified building (Box Flat files, Folder FF11)
    - Columbia University, aerial view (watercolor rendering, Jules Crow) (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, Unidentified university building, 1896 (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, Chemical Engineering Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, proposed Journalism Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, proposed art gallery, 1928 (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, layout of south field (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, East field, "Scheme A" (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, School of Natural Science, two plans on linen (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, Schermerhorn Hall, one plan on linen (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, south field, one plan on linen (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Topographic survey of a part of the grounds of the Bloomingdale Asylum, 1892 (site of Columbia University) (Box Flat files, Folder FF12)
    - Columbia University, pylons, 116th and Broadway (1 blueprint, 1 linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF13)
    - Columbia University, pylons on W. 116th St. (trace drawings) (Box Flat files, Folder FF13A)
    - New-York University (University Heights), half-side elevation of library dome, 1897 (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - Colony Club, front elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - University Club (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - Prospect Park, design for plaza entrance, drawing 2, 1894 (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - JP Morgan Library, detail of loggia (linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - J. P Morgan Library (Box Flat files, Folder FF14)
    - Henry Villard residence (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - University Club (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - Brooklyn Institute of Arts & Sciences (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - New Bellevue Hospital, New York City (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - Columbia University, Philosophy Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF15)
    - C.L. Tiffany house, NYC, 1884 (Monograph series, plate 5A) (Box Flat files, Folder FF16)
    - Pennylvania Station, New York details of main waiting room,1885, plate 310 (Monograph series) (Box Flat files, Folder FF16)
    - Washington Square Arch, north elevation (Monograph series, plate 40) (Box Flat files, Folder FF16)
    - Columbia University, Hamilton Hall, west elevation, college hall (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - Brooklyn Institute (linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - Taylor Residence (linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - Municipal Building (linen)(Monograph series) (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - Mount Royal Club, Montreal, Canada (Box Flat files, Folder FF17)
    - H.A.C. Taylor house (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Knickerbocker Trust Co. (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - University Club (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Gorham Mfg. Co. (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Metropolitan Club (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Joseph Pulitzer house (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - New York Herald building (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - The Bowery Savings Bank (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Thomas Newbold residence (Box Flat files, Folder FF19)
    - Mrs. Clarence Mackay, Roslyn, NY (Box Flat files, Folder FF20)
    - St. George's School, Middletown, RI (Box Flat files, Folder FF21)
    - Columbia University, Low Library plaza photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF22)
    - Pennsylvania Station, New York at street level (Box Flat files, Folder FF23)
    - Municipal Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF24)
    - Madison Square Presbyterian Church, main doorway (Box Flat files, Folder FF18)
    - Arlington Memorial Bridge (Box Flat files, Folder FF25)
    - Harvard Union, Preliminary design living room (Jules Crow) (Box Flat files, Folder FF26)
    - Columbia University, Hamilton Hall, west elevation, college hall/Columbia (RESTRICTED: poor condition) (Box Flat files, Folder FF27)
    - Harvard University, memorial gate, Quincy Street (includes watercolor sketch) (Box Flat files, Folder FF28)
    - Amherst College Art Gallery (3 trace drawings) (Box Flat files, Folder FF29)
    - Proposed parish church, Roslyn, Long Island (Box Flat files, Folder FF30)
    - JP Morgan Library, trace drawing (Box Flat files, Folder FF31)
    - Trinity College, Hartford, CT, Field House & Connection to Trowbridge Memorial (Box Flat files, Folder FF32)
    - War memorial, Florence, Italy (Box Flat files, Folder FF32)
    - Maison de France, New York City (Box Flat files, Folder FF32)
    - Wharton School of Finance & Commerce, University of Pennsylvania, Bird's eye view (Box Flat files, Folder FF32)
    - 3 drawings of unidentified buildings (possibly the Municipal Building) (Box Flat files, Folder FF33)
    - 1 presentation plan of unidentified building (Box Flat files, Folder FF33)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station Improvement, Pittsburgh, PA, 14th St. exit (Box Flat files, Folder FF34)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station Improvement, Pittsburgh, PA, aerial view rain shed (Box Flat files, Folder FF34)
    - Unidentified church, section looking toward chancel (Box Flat files, Folder FF34)
    - New York Institute of the Blind, 5 different views of dormitory units (Box Flat files, Folder FF35)
    - American Academy of Arts & Letters, 1 mounted drawing of south elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF36)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City (plan at waiting room level, plan at street level, plan at concourse level) (Box Flat files, Folder FF37)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, Record Set of Reproductions (Box Flat files, Folder FF38)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF39)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF40)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF41)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF42)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF43)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, New York City, reproductions of station's working drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF44)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station in New York City, proposed mural painting (Box Flat files, Folder FF45)
    - Silk Center Building, Inc., drawing 8, 1925, roof and tank house plan (linen) (Box Flat files, Folder FF46)
    - "House A, House B" (Box Flat files, Folder FF47)
    - "House D," 3 drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF48)
    - "House F," 11 drawings (Box Flat files, Folder FF49)
    - "House G" (Box Flat files, Folder FF50)
    - Early drawings of cottages (Box Flat files, Folder FF51)
    - Sir Ronald Lindsay, full-size details for library/book room (Box Flat files, Folder FF52)
    - Boston Music Hall, Symphony Hall, Boston, plans section and elevation of original design (rejected designs), Plan (neg. 51896), section (neg. 51897) (Box Flat files, Folder FF53)
    - Amherst College Library, Amherst, MA (1968 collection). 4 mounted plans (Box Flat files, Folder FF54)
    - Amherst College Library, Amherst, MA, longitudinal and transverse sections (Box Flat files, Folder FF54A)
    - Pennsylvania Station, Pittsburgh, PA, Lower concourse looking east (Box Flat files, Folder FF55)
    - Pennsylvania Station, Pittsburgh, PA, Upper concourse looking east (Box Flat files, Folder FF55)
    - Middlesex Hospital, Middletown, CT, east elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF56)
    - Middlesex Hospital, Middletown, CT, west elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF56)
    - Middlesex Hospital, Middletown, CT, west elevation, 8-story scheme (Box Flat files, Folder FF56)
    - Middlesex Hospital, Middletown, CT, west elevation, 4-story scheme (Box Flat files, Folder FF56)
    - Tennessee Memorial Competition, 2 plans (Box Flat files, Folder FF57)
    - Girard College Chapel Competition, Philadelphia, PA (Box Flat files, Folder FF57)
    - Custom House, competition drawing, New York (Box Flat files, Folder FF57)
    - Miscellaneous houses (Box Flat files, Folder FF58)
    - Country house for Thomas Jefferson Coolidge, esq., Manchester, MA (reproductions; original drawings owned by John Lastavica and Kitty Coolidge) (Box Flat files, Folder FF59)
    - Prospect Park (Box Flat files, Folder FF60)
    - Prospect Park (Box Flat files, Folder FF61)
    - Grand Central Station Competition, ink on trace, perspective from the north (Box Flat files, Folder FF62)
    - Competition for monumental memorial to Theodore Roosevelt (Box Flat files, Folder FF62)
    - Unidentified project, color rendering (Box Flat files, Folder FF62)
    - Unidentified drawing of bridge (Box Flat files, Folder FF63)
    - Unidentified photo/plan (Box Flat files, Folder FF63)
    - NY Central West Side improvement, City Structure No. 4 and Grade Crossing elimination between 72nd and 80th Street, Manhattan (Box Flat files, Folder FF63)
    - New York University, Library Doors in memory of Stanford White (Box Flat files, Folder FF63)
    - Renderings of unidentified buildings (2 by Jules Crow) (Box Flat files, Folder FF64)
    - Bates Hall, Boston Public Library, 1/2 plan, architrave and jamb. Very poor condition. “Restricted. (Box Flat files, Folder FF65)
    - Brooklyn Institute, north elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF67)
    - San Giorgio dei Schiavi, Venice, Italy, Details of concourse and paneling on walls (Box Flat files, Folder FF67)
    - Cayuga Lake Hotel: view of tower, Interlaken, NY (Box Flat files, Folder FF67)
    - Hotel, Tarrytown Heights, NY (Box Flat files, Folder FF67)
    - Catharine Lorillard Wolfe Residence (proposed), RI (attributed by Leland Roth) (Box Flat files, Folder FF67)
    - Municipal Building, NYC, 2 views by Jules Crow (Box Flat files, Folder FF68)
    - Brooklyn Botanic Garden, Brooklyn, NY (Box Flat files, Folder FF69)
    - State Savings Bank at Detroit, front elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF70)
    - First National Bank Building, 1908 lithograph (poor condition) (Box Flat files, Folder FF71)
    - Judson Memorial Baptist Church (Box Flat files, Folder FF72)
    - Amherst College, Amherst, MA, Preliminary study for general plan (very poor condition) (Box Flat files, Folder FF73)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, NYC, Library and gallery (Box Flat files, Folder FF74)
    - National City Bank, Hong Kong branch, plan (Box Flat files, Folder FF75)
    - New York Terminal Station, Pennsylvania Railroad Company (Box Flat files, Folder FF76)
    - Morgan Library (photo) (Box Flat files, Folder FF76)
    - Columbia University dormitories (photograph, poor condition) (Box Flat files, Folder FF77)
    - Hamilton Hall, Columbia University, NYC (Box Flat files, Folder FF77)
    - New York Herald building, NYC (Box Flat files, Folder FF77)
    - Gorham Co. building photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF77)
    - Gorham Co. building photograph, interior (Box Flat files, Folder FF77)
    - Madison Square Garden, photograph (George P. Hall) (Box Flat files, Folder FF78)
    - City Hall, NYC, photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF78)
    - Harvard University buildings, 2 photographs (Box Flat files, Folder FF78)
    - Town Hall, NYC, exterior photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF79)
    - MMW office rules 1894 (Box Flat files, Folder FF81)
    - French certificate awarded to McKim for 1900 Universal Exposition (Box Flat files, Folder FF81)
    - Pyne Residence, NYC. Floor plans, blueprint, mounted drawing (Box Flat files, Folder FF82)
    - Proposed library, Port Chester, NY (Box Flat files, Folder FF83)
    - Moore Laboratory of Chemistry, Amherst, MA, study for setting for portrait and memorial tablet (Box Flat files, Folder FF83)
    - Davenport Memorial Squash Building, Amherst College, Amherst, MA, south elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF83)
    - Davenport Memorial Squash Building, Amherst College, Amherst, MA, north elevation (Box Flat files, Folder FF83)
    - Chicago World's Fair buildings (photo, very poor condition) (Box Flat files, Folder FF84)
    - Henry Villard residence (watercolor) (Box Flat files, Folder FF85)
    - Pennsylvania Station, New York City, presentation drawing, Jules Crow (watercolor) (Box Flat files, Folder FF86.1)
    - Pennsylvania Station, New York City, presentation drawing, Jules Crow (watercolor) (Box Flat files, Folder FF86.2)
    - Arlington Memorial Bridge (Box Flat files, Folder FF87)
    - Gould Memorial, entrance doors, photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF88)
    - John W. Weeks Bridge, Cambridge, MA, photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF88)
    - United States Post Office, NYC (3 drawings) (Box Flat files, Folder FF89)
    - Winifred Masterson Burke Relief Foundation, White Plains, NY (Box Flat files, Folder FF89)
    - McKinley Birthplace Memorial Competition, front elevation and first floor plan (Box Flat files, Folder FF89)
    - Savoy Plaza Hotel (Box Flat files, Folder FF89)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station, NYC, interior photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF89)
    - Court of the States, 1939 World's Fair, New York, photograph (Box Flat files, Folder FF89)
    - Women's Dormitories South Campus Project (Box Flat files, Folder FF90)
    - Wharton School of Finance and Commerce, main entrance (Box Flat files, Folder FF90)
    - McKinley Birthplace Memorial Competition, front elevation and first floor plan (Box Flat files, Folder FF90)
    - American Military Cemetery, Florence, Italy, prelimary study (Box Flat files, Folder FF90)
    - Princeton University, Field House (Box Flat files, Folder FF90)
    - Bank of Montreal (Wall Street), assorted blueprints (Box Flat files, Folder FF91)
    - Bank of Montreal (Montreal), assorted blueprints; detail drawings of lamps (Box Flat files, Folder FF92)
    - Bank of Montreal (Winnipeg), assorted blueprints (Box Flat files, Folder FF93)
    - Barnard College, structural blueprints (Box Flat files, Folder FF94)
    - Beard Residence, entrance elevation and studies of rooms (Box Flat files, Folder FF95)
    - Bellevue Hospital, blueprints (water main, garage, site plan) (Box Flat files, Folder FF96)
    - Royal Trust Company, drawings on tissue (Box Flat files, Folder FF97)
    - Governors Island Ventilation Building (Box Flat files, Folder FF98)
    - Hotel Pennsylvania Floor Plans (Box Flat files, Folder FF99)
    - Sketch of house for Charles Adsitt, Esq. Hornsville, NY (Box Flat files, Folder FF 100)
      General Note
      This drawing is signed "McKim Mead and Bigelow"
    - Proposed Doors and Porch for St. Bartholomew's Church, 1902 (Box Flat Files, Folder FF 101)
    - Charles H. Williams, Esq. residence, Buffalo, NY, south elevation, 1895 (Box Flat Files, Folder FF 102)
- Series II: Correspondence
  This series consists of approximately 665 hollinger boxes of documents -- primarily letters, but also a large amount of billing correspondence and some contracts. The files also occasionally include small drawings, rough sketches, specifications, photographs and clippings. A small amount of additional correspondence may be located in Series III, Specifications.
  The documents in this series are arranged by project. A box list is available on-site.
- Series III: Specifications
  This series includes approximately 63 boxes of specifications, arranged by project. Additional specifications may be found in Series II, Correspondence.
  - Abbey, Thomas (Box III.1, Folder 1)